Teddy Pendergrass: If You Don't Know Me is a documentary,
music film directed by Olivia Lichtenstein.
The untold and ultimately inspiring story of legendary singer, Teddy Pendergrass, the man poised to be the biggest
R&B artist of all time until the tragic accident that changed his life forever at the age of only 31.
Himself, played by Teddy Pendergrass.
"If You Don't Know Me by Now" is a song written by Kenny Gamble and Leon Huff, and
recorded by the Philadelphia soul musical group Harold Melvin & the Blue Notes.
It became their first hit after being released as a single in September 1972, topping
the US R&B chart and peaking at number 3 on the US Billboard Hot 100.
"If You Don't Know Me by Now" was originally written for Labelle (a
trio led by Patti LaBelle) but they never recorded it.
The song's composers Gamble and Huff gave it to Harold Melvin & the Blue Notes, which featured Teddy Pendergrass as lead
vocalist,
and the actual background vocals done by producers Gamble, Huff, Carl Helm, and Bunny Sigler.
In addition to the single release, the track was
included on their debut album, I Miss You.
Patti LaBelle later made the song part of her concert repertoire in
1982; a live version appears on her 1985 album, Patti.
"If You Don't Know Me by Now" has since been recorded by a number of other artists, most notably the English pop
and soul band Simply Red, who took their version to number one on the Billboard Hot 100 in 1989.
The song was chosen as one of the "Songs of the Century" by the
Recording Industry Association of America (RIAA).
The film explores themes of tragic event, inspiring
story, r&b artist, untold story.
The tone is uplifting.